how would you define a comfort zone
in your own words
well to me your comfort zone is that
is that
your routines your way of being which
distracts you which distracts you from
your discomfort from your fundamental
discomfort from your fundamental
discomfort
so it's that which keeps a lid on your
unhappiness right right so it helps you
right right so it helps you
it helps distract you and shelters you
from dissatisfaction but what
dissatisfaction of what with what
so not necessarily pain
of things not going the way you want
them to go
so dissatisfaction of not being in
control fundamentally
the reason i'm trying to clarify this is
because it's not um
it's it's a it's it's a subtle
it's even it goes on a very subtle level
it's not just a
dissatisfaction on like a kind that
people can easily relate to
it's something you will need to dig in
and dig in and do lots of your cover-ups
and then discover that you depend
on comfort and comfort zone because
basically it provides you well it helps you
it provides you well it helps you
entertain the notion that you are in
control that you do have a say that you are your
that you do have a say that you are your
own
and that you know basically you will be
so it's a sense of that existential
safety that comes from it
so you are the fun
you're dissatisfied because you're not
in control is it
fundamentally you well exactly exactly
so you're dissatisfied because you're
recognizing that even your control
is not up to you it's not it's not
within your say
fundamentally even things you can't
control it's only relatively so
and a relative control it's not really
the control that
you need for the level to reach the
level of safety
you need the absolute control at least
implicitly you need to be your own
like that's that's like you know the and
always that sense of like not seeing a
nature result in possessions
as the buddha would say it results in
acquisitions not because you acquired things
not because you acquired things
uh physically necessarily but because
internally you refuse to admit and acknowledge and
you refuse to admit and acknowledge and
discern
the inherent on each of these things
that they are not controllable thus not
ownable so even if you have no if you
renounce all the worldly possessions but
internally you refuse to face the
nature that fills you with anxiety you
are taking
all of the possessions of the world and
that's why you still have the self view
that's your only way of dealing with it
yeah yeah you don't know how to deal
with that frightening recognition that
you are not your own yeah so what do i
do i make every
i make things my own well exactly or at
least i'll find things that will enable me to
i'll find things that will enable me to
pretend the things of my own
and then just wishfully hope the things
will not go
against the way i wanted them to go
because if they do i will not be able to
deal with it and i will be overwhelmed
by suffering and software and so on
that's where people try to outgrown
anxiety and the whole thing so the co
that's something the comfort zone and
some people you know need more of a
comfort have a bigger comfort zone so
people have a
lesser comfort zone so to speak or
dependency it depends that's what i mean the size
it depends that's what i mean the size
of the conference on the term is your
dependency on the comfort zone
and but either way if you start looking
at it it can be a good symptom to see
how much of a comfort zone you need for
yourself can be a good kind of indicator of how
can be a good kind of indicator of how
much of a cover-up
you're engaging with on that existential
level and even in in mundane worldly terms you
and even in in mundane worldly terms you
know people who are afraid
to even think about the extent of the
comfort zone and just want to commit to
it and not question it and not have the
slightest doubt about it
are usually people that don't get
anywhere in the life
because like even just a worldly
ambition requires taking some risk
requires recognizing degree that you a
certain degree of
non-control so you take the risk things
can go either
but and because of that you kind of
better yourself
so even in worldly terms stepping
outside of the comfort zone
is actually beneficial but as soon as
you step out of that comfort zone
for many people there's anxiety what
might happen
exactly and that's that's where you
force then your mind
to grow if there is no stress there will
be no
response of growth same physically
mentally if there is no tightening of the
if there is no tightening of the
pressure in that sense
there is no reason for body and mind to
adapt to the new pressuring environment
so it won't grow yeah he won't become
stronger but then another person doubles
down and
not double down double was unsheltering
yourself so many
which results then in doubling down on
the weakness increasing the weakness
indirectly but that's the outcome of it
so the more you refuse to
to accept these things on the mental
level that you're not in control that
anxiety is a natural
basically part of the existence uh
the the weaker the more sensitive to it
you will become
and the more you try to get rid of it
the more power you give it
so then how far would you then want to
go
in terms of so speaking from the point
of view of the practice say
how far would you want to go in terms of
questioning or
sort of disturbing your own comfort zone
because would you just like go and risk
your life
because fundamentally you know being
alive is a form of a comfort zone
what what criteria would you use as to
how far to go
give everything up quit your job
everything everything and go and live on
the street because you know
i don't want to depend on the comfort
zone so how far should a person go
so you know why they're going then why
are they still going to practice
okay so you're stepping out of this so
how far they need to step
up so like if somebody say a la person
wants to
practice maybe in ferrara chip do they
just get up walk out not say water and leave
get up walk out not say water and leave
everything behind and just
go and live under the bridge or
somewhere
how far do they have to go they would
have to give up things which are
unwholesome sure but you know
sure but you know
not eating in the afternoon and being a
celibate is yeah requires you to give up things
is yeah requires you to give up things
that aren't wholesome
but yeah like walking out and living
under a bridge also requires you to
not in the afternoon because you won't
have any food
so either way you'll be giving up on
wholesome but there are obviously two
different ways of going about it so
what would what criteria could a person
use them
to know how far he's like too far
outside of my comfort zone testing my
comfort zone uprooting my comfort zone
and how far is just now being ridiculous
and risky
well it would be it's it's a very it's
actually a common you could use a common
sense thing
as as the weather did in the suttas and
i think it's in sebasto
as well certain things to be
abandoned by uh avoiding
so you recognize that
first you kind of recognize the extent
of your comfort zone and i don't mean
the comfort zone is not always simply
defined by comfort physical comfort
more often than not it's the mental
comfort and need and habit and access to
things that's what people kind of are resting
that's what people kind of are resting
on you want to question that
so the most immediate way of questioning
and disturbing your comfort zone is
sense restraint
that will already gonna fill plenty of
people with anxiety and panic
just saying no to their desires and you
realize most people wouldn't even need more than
most people wouldn't even need more than
that
in a way then if afterwards that
they get used to that sense restraint
celibacy and then they feel like they're
like stalling and not really making any
significant progress then they could you
know start digging things a bit further
as
i said dealt with a knife just keep keep
cutting and kept cutting it until
there's no more work for you to be done
at the same time you use the common
sense so
you are not enlightened you are not free
from suffering
you don't know the escape so yes you
need to uproot
your comfort zone and your dependence
upon it but you don't want to do it to
the extent whereby you will factually be
risking your life
because you might die unenlightened and
not knowing anything
so that's because there were those
practices even back in the day and i'm
sure some people would still have those
views today
of like i'll just say yes to everything
or i say no to everything well i just
walk straight that was like in the
suttas it doesn't matter what you you never you
it doesn't matter what you you never you
don't go left you don't go right you
just keep walking straight
so if there is a cliff you'll just walk
through because that's the strength of
your determination
that's how much you will not depend on
any comfort or reason for that matter
but the buddha would say no certain
things are to be abandoned by wisely
avoiding them
wisely you avoid a raging elephant
that's about to stomp you
a rabid dog a group of bandits that
might kill you
why because if they do you will lose
your life
without having achieved the liberation
and so on after you achieve liberation
if you choose to stand in front of an
elephant that's fine
because you have nothing to lose anymore
then you might you might not worry about
it
so you don't want to lose perspective
on your goal which is to be free from
suffering enlightened free from samsara
and so on
so so if you want to question your
comfort zone your question in those
manners so
how can i test or challenge my comfort
zone without risking my life
without risking my life
or compromising my health significantly
that that would occupy all my time
and i wouldn't be able to practice and
so on
and um and then you would you would even
like as i said
you would be obvious there's nothing
there's nothing harmful
and there's nothing stopping you in
practicing sensory strength
even within your current comfort zone so
you don't need to almost
gonna live on the streets and so on no i
just need to be celibate
and there you go your entire world of
comfort is uprooted by that
determination decision
and you would feel it you know without
necessarily having to change the
circumstances significantly
now sure if significant if if the
circumstances are too testing
too too challenging for you to practice
sense restraint then yeah you want to
find somewhere else where you can but
all from the so so the reference point
should be
the the uh the practice the liberation
and the achieving the goal not like some
sort of idea
of i must live on the street independent
of others and never eat for the rest of
my life
you know that's just another thing now
that you're trying to replace your
comfort zone with
certain exactly asceticism this extreme
comfort where you just shun all the comfort it's
where you just shun all the comfort it's
like yeah but then you become dependent
on that
so you you want to get rid of that
dependency on something exactly but not
replace it
because and that's the case when when
you know in the in the
um when you would have said the the
aesthetic practices are ignoble
and uh and don't result in in liberation
it's because
you don't really approve any dependency
you just
shun all the all the um all the comfort
and everything
and that becomes your thing you depend
on constant saying no
and uh either way you you haven't really
approved that existential dependence
which requires you to understand it
understand this thing in which case if
you do you might not need to
you know change things too significantly
if they were already conducive for
wholesomeness
so that's what i mean like it's not that
you must give everything and live under
the root of a tree
i mean if if you see that directly
conducive to those also mental states
then do it and that's when
the buddha would say let those who want
to do that do that the aesthetic
practices as in
meaning let those who know that these
ascetic practices will bring wholesome
things to increase
unwholesome things to discrete decrease
and let them do it but that's not always
the case for some people
shining too much comfort too soon will
actually bring the unwholesome to
increase and wholesome to decrease because the
and wholesome to decrease because the
reference point should be
the practice and liberation and freedom
from suffering
not necessarily a sense of duty and what
you kind of romantically assumed you
must be
living with and giving up but just yeah
so
to be free from suffering to be free
from that
satisfaction to be free from that uh
yeah that uh basically from the
dissatisfaction that arises on account
of
fundamental existential non control
so that's your goal that's your criteria
you don't want to be depend and that's
that's like
you don't want to be depending on
anything it's when that's uh the buddha
would say
you don't find anything as a support
your consciousness is not supported by
anything any other um aggregate and so on and the
any other um aggregate and so on and the
similarly was that uh the cow
the deflated cow with the wounds that if
it leans on the wall
it's being eaten by the creatures that
live on the wall if it lays on the
ground it's been eaten by the creatures
they're living
if it stands up it's being eaten by the
creatures that are flying the air
either way if you if he tries to use
anything as a support
it's being devoured and that's it if you
try to use
anything as your comfort zone on account
of which you don't face the reality that
you are
a wounded animal subjected to death not
in your control and so on
you will suffer not because of the
wounds but because you're trying to
cover it up
so the dissatisfaction comes because you
don't want to acknowledge and admit that
you're not in control because it's too
frightening so you said like pain is not the problem
so you said like pain is not the problem
pain is not a problem just that
resistance towards it which makes it
painful that's that's what the dukkha is
yeah physical discomfort is not the dukkha
physical discomfort is not the dukkha
that
um that you should be sort of freeing
yourself from because the body is not in
your control you can't feel yourself
from it that's why even arahants would
say any disturbance that's left now after
any disturbance that's left now after
i become another hunt and it disturbs
this left it's on account of this body
until it breaks apart so any annoyance
assuming it's just physical
none of that will cause mental anguish
or suffering
so you want to be doing things gradually
to but yeah in terms of the practice you
want to be revealing
the nature of things well exactly you
don't want to just go through the
motions of
giving things up and and questioning and
challenging my comfort zone
you want to have the context context
being i am existential depending upon a
sense of control
and that's basically my comfort zone is
the symptom of that
so i don't want to be existentially
depending i as will
say i don't want to be using anything as
a support
internally so i just want everything
that i use to remind me of the nature of
things well yeah that's like if you gain
well yeah that's like if you gain
perspective sure you want to so you want
to do things that keep that
that can contain sustain that context
alive yeah so it's you
there are obvious things that you will
have to stop doing things that will be
completely and unequivocally always distracting you
and unequivocally always distracting you
from that context
sensuality carelessness breaking the
precepts uh taking
drugs alcohol and so on well decoration
that's what says uh
uh asks of us to be abandoned by um
using by using for requisites properly yeah
by using for requisites properly yeah
you know just for covering
the shameful parts by rewriting the
purpose of things you use them for
not for beautification decoration but
for the practical
basically sustenance and need until you
have fulfilled your goal
so that's another thing so you would
know exactly
what it's conducive and what it's not
conducive uh the clearer your goal is
uh the clearer your goal is
so most people practice them i have a
vague notion of some goal but they don't
really they can't relate to it internally they
they can't relate to it internally they
don't see a direct
line between if i do this will result in
that and
it's all kind of over there and wishful
thinking and hoping that it will
result like the way they wanted to
resolve but
do you are you clear as to what needs to
be done
in terms of the dharma practice like as
we would say do you like
you hear you measure the task and then
the inspiration comes because i know
exactly how much you need to do
so internally your goal should be to not
depend on anything
you know any feeling or any perception
or any circumstance
any basically anything that provides you
with comfort and that sense of sort of
like uh
resting upon something like i'm safe
here you are not in any position of
safety so that should be the context you should
so that should be the context you should
only be increasing in your practice
the recognition of that context because
that's the true way to find the safety
then because so i step outside of my comfort
because so i step outside of my comfort
zone
in the right way so and it might make
you tougher might make you grow a bit
but if you do it just for the sake of
doing it you are not going to get any
substantial wisdom i mean you can do it with the
wisdom i mean you can do it with the
intention to try and learn from it and
so on
but even then then you use the common
sense so let me know do to the extent
that i cannot sustain like i can go and
live under the bridge without
anything or anyone for a bit before i
get sick
and basically die or something or i can
go and live in in this
tiger infested jungle but there's a good
chance like you know i might die within a month
like you know i might die within a month
because there are man-eaters there and
so on
so well that's foolish then
because there are plenty of other
non-life-threatening ways
that you can challenge and uproot your
confidence on
be celibate don't eat in the afternoon
restrain your eyes nose ears don't go
after the pleasure of sense objects
that will shake you right to the core
because the core of the human
existence is that uh central being being
of centrality being that depends upon
the pleasures
uh obtained through the object of the
senses and would have said that
doesn't know any other escape from the
discomfort from the uh
unpleasant feeling except uh sensuality
that's why he's like a double sort of
twice bound by it first because he wants
bound by it first because he wants
pleasure but also because that's his
only way
of avoiding pain and discomfort
it's the distraction so the only way to
deal with things
to deal with the nature is to turn and
turn a blind eye to it to distract
yourself yeah
find things to do removed removing
distractions obviously you will reveal the nature
obviously you will reveal the nature
oh yeah exactly gradually if you if you
if you refuse to engage with
distractions first you're going to have just a good
first you're going to have just a good
old day playing plane
day-to-day boredom but if you still
don't give in and try to distract
yourself yeah dead boredom you're gonna start
yeah dead boredom you're gonna start
feeling the weight of it and then you
realize oh this is something much more
because you okay so you start you start
feeling the weight of it meaning
more anxiety the anxiety that comes from
seeing the nature of you not being
controlled by nature
but if you stick with that long enough
and don't try to run away from that
nature which is well you will force your
mind to grow
because that's how you grow that's how
you become stronger by
by stressing it so yeah sure you could
stress it too much
and then just have a breakdown because
you can't bear that anxiety
but if you're sense restrained
beforehand if you kept the presets
beforehand if you don't have the
negative unwholesome outlets of your
behavior like bad habits and so on
you are actually compressing it and
you're forcing it to adapt
so once you become more and more used to
anxiety and not trying to outrun it
then you realize that the only reason it
was unpleasant is you because you kept
trying to outrun it
not because in itself sense of control
sorry sense of the non-control
that people can recognize in a nature
it's quite neutral
there's nothing there's nothing wrong or
unpleasant like you don't suffer on
account of
you have no control over the tree or the
river and that doesn't bother you why not
and that doesn't bother you why not
because it's still the phenomenon of
non-control that you recognize
it doesn't bother you because you're not
personally invested in controlling it
so then you realize that when any sense
of non-control
bothers you it's only that bother is
actually caused by your investment of
i want to control this or i assume to
control this
so now the recognition of non-control is
undermining that
but if you remove your assumption no
amount of non-control can cause your
suffering it's just as it is
the way things are in that sense like
things are truly a nietzsche
but you see it or not the only reason a
nietzsche will be dukkha is if you
ignore the fact that they are a nietzsche so
the fact that they are a nietzsche so
it's because of your ignorance that
anita is dukkha not because in itself
anichi you see you won't at any stage
you see you won't at any stage
change that fact of the nature
inconceivable inconceivable
i'll practice in touch with you nature
changes no you
stop going against that you stop
entertaining assumptions that are
diametrically opposed to an each to the
nature that you recognize
so anxiety is a good symptom basically
if you're bothered by anxiety it's not
because anxiety bothers you it's because
of your views that are opposed to that
which anxiety is revealing
which is non-control so stop
entertaining control
stop entertaining the the control of
through your possessions of your
possessions stop entertaining ownership
because all you need to do is start
thinking about it and even things that
you do
own just think about it can you prevent
them from disappearing or something
happening to them inconceivable
maintain that context and you are
eroding the ownership
the longer you're maintaining the less
and less ownership there will be
remaining that's not to say that's going to be
that's not to say that's going to be
pleasant or inspiring quite the opposite
but once that's so once that ownership
is
gone so to speak then that's this
passion there's still a nature
but that anxiety there
changes well because you're not trying
to outrun it you're not trying to get
rid of it which means it's not going to
be unpleasant
it's going to be just a neutral state of
things so
you wouldn't really call it anxiety
anymore from that point of view yes
and you you said in the past that
you might have called it uh being alert
alertness recognition
that yeah things might end next second
because yeah they might the mindfulness
of death that they would encourage
that's exactly that first you'll be
anxious because you the assumption of
life is so strong
but if you have a brutal assumption of
life then it's just recognition that
yeah i literally
might die within the next in and out
breath and it's just you're alert to that
and it's just you're alert to that
fundamental
very profound recognition somehow from
anxiety when you understand things when
you have a right get right view that
anxiety changes into
alert mindfulness it doesn't change you
always was that
that's the thing anxiety is already
alertness that you're resisting which is
why that alertness is unpleasant
that's what mindfulness responsibility
uh recognition of your situation are all
kind of unpleasant recognition for
petuna so and that's why pollution cannot
so and that's why pollution cannot
become a soda panna
by chance by miracle or by by technique
because the direction of saudi party the
right view and freedom is through the
anxiety that entire being of gothujana is geared
that entire being of gothujana is geared
against
always by default ownership
sense of self self view all of that
is against the that which which is
behind anxiety
and that's why anxiety is so terrifying
and unpleasant
so even when people practice to be free
from anxiety
that practice will not result in
liberation because it's taking you away from that
because it's taking you away from that
which is inherently
revealed by anxiety that you cannot bear
so the practice should not be
freeing you from anxiety it should be
making you less disturbed by anxiety
you get like saying being free from
anxiety means of being free from
existence while you still exist it's a
while you still exist it's a
contradiction in terms it's impossible
anxiety is the existence or the
existence is behind the anxiety
whichever you want to call it but when
it's a problem
so if it's a problem it's not because of
existence or the anxiety
it's because of your assumptions in
regard to it
so the practice should be enabling you
to to
to accept that and endure it and then
eventually not even being bothered by it
and then see exactly what's there
and that's the direction of sota party
that's what i said before like
when the suttas say or at the moment of
death they will achieve the fruit these
various noble disciples not because some
mystical things happen in the moment of
death is because death is at the end of that
is because death is at the end of that
direction that you don't want to look at
when you experience anxiety in
day-to-day life
but you will have to go through it
eventually so the one with the right
view goes that way even before he dies
goes that way even before he dies
and then arakan has fully walked that
way and freed himself
that's why death does not apply to him
anymore yeah that's what a certain
manner can
can become can become an arahant at the
moment of death yeah
because that's the direction where he's
thought about he already yeah
he's facing that nature yeah yeah of
course with no distractions
that's a danger for the any distractions
for the
social that's why he doesn't make any
progress it's the distractions yeah they
just keep him
basically slowing him down from heading
the way that he's heading yeah
so that's why all sort of all the noble
disciples to do is not be negligent and
make the effort towards distractions
because if he doesn't make the effort of
destruction what he's left with is his
right view which means he's left with
the practice
so all he needs to do is abstain from
unwholesome things and he'll become
another he doesn't need to do anything on top of that